Okay, good
morning
everyone. We are
going
to cover דף י"א daf Yud Aleph of פסחים Pesachim this morning.
I know we got a little ways into י"א עמוד א'. Yud
Aleph Amud Aleph. I'm just going to backtrack from the משנה mishna
on י' עמוד ב' Yud Amud Bet quickly, a little bit outside,
and try to make our way through the sort of general flow
of the סוגיה sugya this morning,
which covers י"א עמוד א' Yud Aleph Amud Aleph and the top
of י"א עמוד ב', Yud Aleph Amud Bet,
which is the bulk of the דף. daf. After that, there's a
new משנה mishna and then the beginning of a discussion about how
much time people can be expected to err in their assessment of
the time, jumping off of the discussion in that משנה mishna about
the times for the end of driving benefit from חמץ chametz and
eating חמץ, chametz, etc. That's at the end. But
basically the סוגיה sugya that covers most of the דף daf today
is a סוגיה sugya which is in a sense analyzing a debate
in our משנה mishna between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and חכמים Chachamim
and using it really as a jumping off point to try to
get some conceptual understanding of in general under what circumstances would one
make a גזירה gezeira to avoid a situation where one could come
to be עובר over an איסור דאורייתא issur d'Oraita and what kinds
of factors we factor in in our consideration. You know,
interacting with an item which is similar to the thing which would
lead to an איסור דאורייתא issur d'Oraita or is it about whether
how much we normally comfortably interact with an item or how cautious
we are about the item in general, the concept of בדילי מיניה
bedilei minei or whether there are certain areas of הלכה halacha in
which people are just generally more cautious. And if they are already
more cautious then a גזירה gezeira is not needed. And it's a,
you know, has a maybe broader implications for thinking in general about
how to sort of how to think about the application of the
concept rabbinically and legally of עשו סייג לתורה, assu syag laTorah, of
really making fences around the תורה. Torah. So that's sort of just
a broad view. And along the way we're going to bring in
cases dealing with חמץ chametz as our jumping off point, dealing with
חדש chadash and grain issues,
dealing with a בכור, bechor, dealing with הלכות שבת. hilchot Shabbat. So
it's sort of get a little mini survey of various issues around
this question of making a גזירה. gezeira. So back on י' עמוד
ב' Yud Amud Bet just for a moment, I'll try to just
skim through a little bit outside and then we'll pick up where
we left off on י"א עמוד א'. Yud Aleph Amud Aleph. Also
just one timing note, if we're able to end a drop earlier,
I'm going to try to get down to the 8:15 תפילה Tefilla
closer to on time, but we try not to sacrifice our understanding
of the דף daf for that. Obviously please feel free to ask
questions and we'll challenge each other and try to come to a
clear understanding as a result. So the משנה mishna on י' עמוד
ב' Yud Amud Bet at the bottom: רבי יהודה אומר בודקין. Rabbi
Yehuda omer bodekin. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda gives these three seeming different
time periods for בדיקת חמץ: bedikat chametz: the night of the 14th,
the 14th in the morning, and around the time at which חמץ
chametz needs to be destroyed, mostly roughly midday for now. And the
sages say, חכמים אומרים לא בדק אור ארבעה עשר יבדוק בארבעה עשר
לא בדק בארבעה עשר יבדוק בתוך המועד לא בדק בתוך המועד יבדוק
לאחר המועד.
Chachamim omrim lo badak or arba'ah asar yivdok b'arba'ah asar lo badak
b'arba'ah asar yivdok b'toch hamoed lo badak b'toch hamoed yivdok
l'achar hamoed. Big מחלוקת, machloket, רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, whether these
three times of the חכמים Chachamim essentially are equivalent to רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda with just the difference of the rest of ערב פסח
Erev Pesach that חכמים Chachamim allow בדיקה bedika on, or whether I
think a more literal reading תוספות Tosafot suggests is actually חכמים Chachamim
allow בדיקה bedika all the way through פסח Pesach itself if one
hasn't done בדיקה bedika prior to that, linked up תוספות Tosafot explicitly
say to the debate that תוספות Tosafot perceives them having with רש"י
Rashi about what the purpose of בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz is in
general. And the גמרא's Gemara interested here and then a sort of
after-comment within the משנה mishna which maybe universally held, we don't have
any debate about it: מה שמשייר יניחנו בצנעה כדי שלא יהא צריך
בדיקה אחריו. ma shemeshayer yanichenu b'tzina kedei shelo yehei tzarich bedika achara.
That which gets left over after the בדיקה bedika gets put aside
in some secure place so that we don't need further בדיקה. bedika.
We know where all the חמץ chametz that we've now collected is
and we can protect it so we don't have a situation of
now not seeing some, needing to do any further בדיקה. bedika. Okay,
so the גמרא's Gemara question initially has to do with its understanding
of the plain sense of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda comment that these
are actually three distinct times during which בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz should
take place. And the גמרא Gemara there, you know, cites three different
פסוקים pesukim or three different instances that describe getting rid of your
חמץ chametz as a way of saying רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually
requires בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz in these, in all three of these
three distinct times. And then the גמרא Gemara goes on to essentially
reject that position and say no, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and חכמים
Chachamim basically agree. three that you if you haven't done בדיקה bedika
ideally you should do בדיקה bedika in the first one of these
times and if you haven't you could do it in the second.
You didn't do it in the first or second you could do
it in the third of these times and the only point of
their debate is that חכמים chachamim go further to say that even
after the time at which חמץ chametz becomes prohibited you still if
you haven't done בדיקה bedika at that point you still should and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no. Now let's pick up just inside
a little bit more about three lines from the bottom on י'
עמוד ב' Yud Amud Bet about two-thirds of the way across the
line. והכא בהכא קמיפלגי. V'hacha bhacha kamipalgi. Here's what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and חכמים chachamim are really arguing about. מר סבר מקמי איסורא
אין בתר איסורא לא גזירה דלמא אתי למיכל מיניה ורבנן סברי לא
גזרינן.
Mar savar mikamei issura in batar issura la gezeira dilma
ati l'meichal minei v'rabbanan savri lo gazrinan.
So מר Mar here is clearly רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we know
who the two positions are here. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has
the position מקמי איסורא אין בתר איסורא לא. Mikamei issura in batar
issura la.
So prior to the time in which חמץ chametz is prohibited we
do do בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz if we haven't done it anytime
up until that point we should do it but after the time
in which חמץ chametz becomes prohibited then we don't do בדיקת חמץ
bedikat chametz anymore גזירה דלמא אתי למיכל מיניה gezeira dilma ati l'meichal
minei
because we're concerned that if you do בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz after
the time in which חמץ chametz is prohibited you're going to in
the process of the בדיקה bedika actually you know come and eat
some of the חמץ chametz which you're checking and חמץ chametz is
prohibited דאורייתא d'Oraita and therefore the importance of בדיקה bedika is not
so important that we would cause you to do בדיקה bedika in
a situation where you might come to eat from it. So we
have רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's what's going to emerge as possibly a
general position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that we do make decrees
to avoid איסורי דאורייתא issurei d'Oraita in a situation where we're concerned
that you're going to come to you know consume or interact with
in an in a prohibited way the thing that's the subject of
the activity. ורבנן סברי לא גזרינן. V'rabbanan savri lo gazrinan. The rabbis
say no we don't make such a decree. We trust you we
allow you or we don't feel it's necessary to legislate against that
concern. ומי גזר רבי יהודה דלמא אתי למיכל מיניה והתנן משקרב העומר
יוצאין ומוצאין שוקי ירושלים שהם מלאים קמח וקלי שלא ברצון חכמים Umi
gazar Rabbi Yehuda dilma ati l'meichal minei vehanan mishekarev ha'omer yotzin umotzin
shukei yerushalayim shehem mele'im kemach v'kali shelo b'ratzon chachamim י"א עמוד א'.
Yud Aleph Amud Aleph.
So is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda really concerned that we should make
decrees lest one come to consume something and violate thereby an איסור
דאורייתא? issur d'Oraita? Because we have a משנה mishna in מנחות Menachot
which says that when the עומר omer was offered from the time
that the עומר omer was offered on the sixteenth of ניסן Nisan
people would go out and find already prepared in the markets of
ירושלים Yerushalayim that they were already filled with קמח וקלי kemach v'kali
with you know grain flour and some kind of cooked or popped
or roasted grains and this was not in accordance with the wish
of the sages. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir's position. רבי יהודה אומר ברצון חכמים היו עושים. Rabbi Yehuda
omer b'ratzon chachamim hayu osim. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
no this was in accordance with the with the sages.
There wasn't any opposition to doing what needed to be done here
which what we understand is that if at the time that the
עומר omer was offered people went out into the marketplace and found
all these things and then that means that people were interacting with
the with the grain products they weren't eating them but they were
interacting with the grain products prior to the time in which the
eating was permitted which is certainly something which is risky because one
might come to eat from the grain products in the process of
the preparation. And and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says this was fine
ברצון חכמים היו עושים b'ratzon chachamim hayu osim ולא קגזר רבי יהודה
דלמא אתי למיכל מיניה. v'lo kagazar Rabbi Yehuda dilma ati l'meichal minei.
So it seems clear that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda here does not
have the concern. He was did not make a decree that you
shouldn't prepare the the grain products prior to the time that they
become permitted in for consumption.
He doesn't have this גזירה דלמא אתי למיכל מיניה. gezeira dilma ati
l'meichal minei. So this raises a question on רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's
position earlier in which we say that the reason רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda seems to stop the period of בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz at
the time of the prohibition of consumption of חמץ chametz is because
he is concerned דלמא אתי למיכל מיניה. dilma ati l'meichal minei. Clear
so far? Yep. Okay I know we covered this already yesterday but
I want since this is the core issue רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's
position we're just going to flow again through. אמר רבא Amar Rava
some have the version of רבא Rava שאני חדש מתוך שלא התרת
לו אלא על ידי קיטוף הוא זכור. Shani chadash mitoch shelo hitarta
lo ela al yedei kituf hu zachor.
So רבא Rava says no we can retain רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's
position in principle that we do make decrees when we're afraid that
you're going to come to consume something and violate an איסור דאורייתא
issur d'Oraita we do make a decree that you not come and
interact with it any in any way and it's just that חדש
chadash where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does not make the decree is
different. מתוך שלא התרת לו אלא על ידי קיטוף הוא זכור Mitoch
shelo hitarta lo ela al yedei kituf hu zachor because it's only
permitted through a slightly different process of preparation. It requires if we
look at רש"י Rashi here קצירה. ketzira. I don't know what the
general מנהג minhag of our study is but I tend in דף
יומי Daf Yomi style learning to refer to רש"י Rashi just for
a quick explanation. Okay
great so so. Rashi's on the second line of י"א עמוד א',
Yud Aleph Amud Aleph, רבי יהודה אומר מתוך שלא התרת לו קצירה
כדרך כל השנה אלא בידיים קוטפין המלילות מן הקרקע. Rabbi Yehuda omer
mi-toch shelo hitarta lo ketzira k'derech kol ha'shana ela b'yadayim kotfin ha'mlilot
min hakarka.
Rashi points out that the way of harvesting the grain when it's
prior to the time that the עומר Omer was permitted
was not קצירה כדרך כל השנה, ketzira k'derech kol ha'shana, the normal
way of harvesting, אלא בידיים קוטפין המלילות, ela b'yadayim kotfin ha'mlilot, but
rather the grain was harvested prepared by hand because the עומר, Omer,
you were not allowed to harvest anything prior to the harvest of
the עומר, Omer, עומר ראשית קצירכם. Omer reishit k'tzirchem. The עומר Omer
is supposed to be the first of the harvest and therefore one
shouldn't harvest anything prior. There was a שינוי shinoy which was done.
Rashi continues on, just look at the first short line of Rashi,
זכור הוא את איסור החדש על ידי שינוי המעשה ולא אתי למיכל.
Zachor hu et issur ha'chadash al yedei shinoy ha'ma'aseh v'lo ati l'meichal.
There's a שינוי, shinoy, a change, a concept we're familiar with in
other areas of הלכה halacha like שבת. Shabbat. Sometimes things which might
otherwise be prohibited, rabbinically prohibited, one could do if one does it
in a different way. And the גמרא Gemara articulates it very nicely:
through doing something with a שינוי, shinoy, זכור, zachor, you remember whatever
it is that you need to remember, that this is a time
in which it's generally prohibited and that's the function of the שינוי.
shinoy.
And so therefore kind of סייג syag also.
Yes. Now this סייג syag isn't only to prohibit an action, a
סייג syag can also
be to do something in a way
that will stimulate your awareness so you won't do it. Prohibited. Yes.
Excellent, excellent. So the שינוי shinoy had that effect. In so far
as you're not allowed to harvest. Yeah, but in other words, okay,
right. It's the nature.
Yeah.
Okay, good.
So מתוך שלא התרת לו אלא על
ידי קיטוף הוא זכור.
mi-toch shelo hitarta
lo ela al yedei kituf hu zachor.
Because you only allowed it through קיטוף, kituf, through this
שינוי shinoy means, one will remember and therefore חדש chadash because it
has a שינוי, shinoy, therefore it doesn't need a גזירה. gezeira. That's
sort of the general, or one could say there is a גזירה
gezeira in some way and so an additional גזירה gezeira that takes
interacting with it off the table entirely is not necessary and therefore
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda could say that this was ברצון חכמים b'ratzon
chachamim and no גזירה gezeira is needed.
He has a different answer. I was thinking, as opposed to the
way it's harvested is different, you can say that just the situation's
different, as opposed to me being in my own house among my
own חמץ. chametz. Here we are in the marketplace.
No. I didn't do this yesterday. But you know, or whatever, okay,
fine. Yes, so good, there are other answers given and in fact
this answer is ultimately really going to be rejected but it's a
start. But if none of the answers accord with yours then bring
yours again when we get a little further. So אמר ליה אביי:
amar lei Abaye: תינח בשעת קטיפה טחינה והרקדה מאי איכא למימר? teinach
b'shat kitifa, t'china v'harkada mai ika l'meimar? So אביי Abaye says to
רבא Rava or רבה, Rabbah, okay, that's great at the moment of
harvesting then there's something which is done differently to remind you. But
let's say one group of people is harvesting, now they bring it
to another group of people. We saw from the משנה mishna that
what's in the marketplace is flour and cooked grain and therefore this
is not just something which was harvested, it went through further stages
of preparation which includes טחינה, t'china, grinding, והרקדה v'harkada and sifting to
get it to the stage that it's in when it's found in
the marketplace. But we don't have any indication that some שינוי shinoy
was done there. So now you have some other set of people
or even the same people in a different stage of preparation who
are doing things in the normal way and therefore they might really
come to eat it. Therefore the reason of having a שינוי shinoy
obviating the need for a גזירה gezeira doesn't apply in these later
stages. And how can רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda therefore say that no
גזירה gezeira was needed if we think that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
holds a general principle that we should have a גזירה gezeira in
a situation where we're afraid that one might come to eat something
which is prohibited? הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, no problem. טחינה
בריחיא דיד הרקדה על גב נפא. t'china b'reichaya d'yad, harkada al gav
naffa. No problem. In fact there was a שינוי shinoy in each
of these places as well. The grinding was done with a hand
millstone which was something which again was more difficult to use. I
think רש"י Rashi comments as opposed to a water millstone. Right. רש"י
ומשנינן טחינה לא היו טוחנין אותו בריחיים של מים אלא בריחיים של
יד דהוי שינוי לזכרון. Rashi: u-m'shaninan t'china, lo hayu tochnin oto b'reichayim
shel mayim ela b'reichayim shel yad d'hava shinoy l'zikaron. They didn't grind
with the water millstone which was the regular one but rather with
a hand millstone which was a change in order to enable people
to remember that they're doing something different. Now I imagine that it
was not just an aesthetic change but it was also probably less
productive or less effective is my hunch and that also heightens the
awareness.
Exactly, a water powered mill
and a hand grinder.
Right.
And then that explains similar to the קיטוף ביד kituf b'yad as
opposed to whatever was the general way. It reduces the productivity which
is also a way of heightening one's awareness that this is something
which is not ideal or a different form. As well as the
sifting was done על גבי נפא, al gabay naffa, on the back
of the sifter, was turned upside down and done in the reverse,
again a less effective method.
רש"י Rashi specifies water because there's
also...
Yeah,
yeah, yeah. He gives this one choice when there may have been
multiple alternative options as were- that were typical as well. Okay, so
this seems to resolve the issue. One just one side note is
that I wasn't able to locate in my quick looking around whether
the גמרא Gemara actually says this anywhere else. In other words, this
answer that the שינויים shinuyim were done in the grinding and the
sifting, I didn't see that the גמרא Gemara comments on this in
מנחות. Menachot. It seems to be only here where the question is
asked. I didn't check the parallel סוגיא, sugya, but I didn't see
any reference to it. It seems like it may be worth checking
on our own. I'll try to look it up as well, that
only here where the question is asked in the context of our
סוגיא sugya of trying to figure out רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
this answer given, maybe pressured by the desire to get some clarity
in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. We say this thing, but it
may not in its own original context be mentioned. I'm not certain,
something that needs to be checked. Sometimes in trying to understand someone's
position in the local context where they're being fleshed out, a new
answer might emerge or be given.
Okay, so we resolved that indeed there is a שינוי shinoy in
these places as well and therefore that's why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
does not make a גזירה. gezera. אלא, הא דתנן, Ella hadetnan now
I think we're up to where we left off. אלא Ella, הא
דתנן hadetnan, קוצרים בית השלחים kotzrin beyt hashlachim ושבעמקים veshebe'amakim אבל לא
גודשים aval lo godshim ואוקימנא כרבי יהודה ve'okimna keRabbi Yehuda מאי איכא
למימר? mai ikka lemeimar? Ah,
but we have another משנה mishna which says that we can do
harvesting even though in general we don't harvest anything until the עומר,
Omer, although unless it's done with a שינוי, shinoy, but we don't
have any mention of harvesting with a שינוי shinoy in the following
משנה mishna about things that can be harvested prior to the עומר.
Omer. קוצרים בית השלחים, kotzrin beyt hashlachim, we can harvest from fields
that were irrigated as opposed to fields that were nourished by rain.
ושבעמקים, veshebe'amakim, and fields that were in valleys, there's a lot of
textual variance here, maybe בית השלחים שבעמקים beyt hashlachim shebe'amakim that it's
only one item or that בעמקים be'amakim might have some different meaning.
But either way, these are the fields which as רש"י Rashi explains,
these are fields which their produce is often because of their environmental
circumstances less good produce and therefore the עומר Omer is never going
to be brought from these fields. And we have the principle that
fields from which the עומר Omer is never going to be brought
because they don't produce the nicest grain, one can actually harvest prior
to the עומר. Omer. Still one can't eat from those things until
the עומר Omer has been brought, but one can harvest from those
fields prior to the עומר. Omer. And this is רש"י Rashi goes
through, has to do with a conflict between two פסוקים pesukim about
the עומר. Omer. One which says when you harvest and you bring
the עומר, Omer, which would seem like maybe some harvesting is allowed
before you bring the עומר, Omer, whereas elsewhere it says עומר Omer
the first of your harvest which makes it seem like the עומר
Omer has to be first. So we say fields from which the
עומר Omer could be brought, fields that have the nicest grain,
those kinds of fields you can't even harvest from except maybe with
a שינוי, shinoy, but fields from which the עומר Omer would never
be brought because they're not as nice can actually be harvested from
prior to the harvesting of the עומר. Omer. However, ואוקימנא כרבי יהודה
ve'okimna keRabbi Yehuda we establish there based on a later- What does
that mean that like, you know, the עומר Omer was brought from
some place really close, so if I had the perfect field, but
you know, 50 miles away I can cut it?
No, I think it's by genre of field. In other words, even
if the עומר Omer was not brought from that field, but it's
the type of field that the עומר Omer could have been brought
from, you still couldn't harvest from that field until the עומר Omer
was brought.
So, so again,
based on a later phrase from that
משנה, mishna, the גמרא Gemara there in מנחות Menachot we determine that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the attributed author of this משנה. mishna.
So now we have רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying that one can
harvest
grain before the עומר Omer even though here there's no שינוי. shinoy.
So again, this is another objection to רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position
that we in general make a גזירה gezera lest one come to
interact with something prohibited and previously we had resolved all the counterexamples
by saying there's a שינוי, shinoy, but here there's no mention of
any שינוי. shinoy. It's simply harvesting is allowed, but wouldn't one therefore
be at risk of coming to eat it and therefore wouldn't רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda want to make a גזירה gezera in this case?
So this, even though we have been able to make previous resolutions
to אביי's Abaye general answer that when there's a שינוי shinoy גזירה
gezera is not needed, this seems to reject אביי's Abaye position. אלא
אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye gives a different answer.
חדש בדיל מיניה, chadash badil minei, חמץ לא בדיל מיניה. chametz lo
badil minei. חדש Chadash as a category is something which is prohibited
for significant periods of time, right, until the 16th of ניסן Nissan
all the previous year's grain is not allowed to be eaten and
therefore we're generally cautious about חדש. chadash. I guess we perceive חדש
chadash in general as something which is prohibited to us until it's
permitted sort of conceptually. And therefore people are generally cautious about it.
Something which people are generally cautious about we don't need to enact
another גזירה gezera lest you come to eat it and therefore we
can answer for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in this משנה mishna the
reason he would allow קצירה בית השלחים ketzira beyt hashlachim is because
this is חדש chadash and חדש chadash one is going to be
cautious about and one's not just going to come to eat it.
doesn't require a שינוי shinuy in interacting with it, sort of by
its status as חדש chadash a person is going to be cautious
about it. Whereas חמץ, chametz, לא בדיל מיניה, lo badeil minei, חמץ
chametz as an as a food as an item is food. חמץ
chametz is typical food, it's not something there are eight days a
year or so in which we're cautious about not eating it but
that has to do with the time of year, the item itself,
which is
produced leavened food, we're not generally cautious about and therefore something like
that requires an extra גזירה gezeira and that's why for רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda we're גוזר gozer in our משנה mishnah not to do
בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz after the time that חמץ chametz becomes אסור.
assur. Okay, so that is
אביי'ס Abaye's answer, that it depends on whether it's something which people
are separating from or not. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, דרבי יהודה אדרבי
יהודה קשיא, de-Rabbi Yehuda ad Rabbi Yehuda kashya, דרבנן אדרבנן לא קשיא.
de-Rabbanan ad Rabbanan lo kashya. So now רבא Rava asks a question.
Okay, wait a second. You we set up a contradiction between רבי
יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's position in our משנה mishnah in which he says
that we
are גוזר gozer דילמא אתי למיכל מיניה dilma atei le-meichal minei lest
you come to eat from something against the משנה mishnah in מנחות
Menachot in which it seems like he doesn't have that concern about
the food which is out in the marketplace. However, we didn't raise
a similar, a parallel but opposite objection to the contradiction between the
positions of the רבנן. Rabbanan. The רבנן Rabbanan in our משנה mishnah
remember said that one can continue to do בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz
all the way until maybe even into the מועד, moed, but certainly
after the time in which חמץ chametz is prohibited, so therefore they
don't seem to be concerned that we need to make a גזירה,
gezeira, and yet in the משנה mishnah in מנחות Menachot about the
grain being out in the marketplace, that was according to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir who sort of represents חכמים chachamim or he says it's
שלא ברצון חכמים, shelo birtzon chachamim, that חכמים chachamim don't think it's
good to have that grain out and therefore it seems like חכמים
chachamim themselves would be גוזר gozer דילמא אתי למיכל מיניה dilma atei
le-meichal minei in such a case. So why did we get all
worked up about the contradiction between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and those
two and not רבנן? Rabbanan? And so we say, לא קשיא, lo
kashya, no, the fact that we didn't raise that contradiction between רבנן
Rabbanan is itself not a problem.
רבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא כדישנינן. Rabbi Yehuda ad Rabbi Yehuda
lo kashya kideshaninan. We already resolved the contradiction between these two משניות
mishnayot of the positions of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda with this idea
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks we need to make a גזירה
gezeira when one is not already separating from an item but when
an item is classified as something that we would separate from, we
do need to make a גזירה, gezeira, so that we've already resolved.
דרבנן אדרבנן נמי לא קשיא. De-Rabbanan ad Rabbanan nami lo kashya. And
now the distinction between the rabbinic positions about whether we need to
make a גזירה gezeira when one might come to eat something or
interact with something prohibited is also not a problem. Why? הוא עצמו
מחזר עליו לשרפו מיכל קאכיל מיניה? Hu atzmo mechazer alav le-sorfo, meichal
ka-achil minei? Right, think about the position of the בדיקת חמץ. bedikat
chametz. Why did the rabbis, if we take מנחות Menachot as the
default that in general the rabbis were concerned, why did they not
make a גזירה gezeira in the case of בדיקת חמץ? bedikat chametz?
Because הוא עצמו מחזר עליו לשרפו. hu atzmo mechazer alav le-sorfo. What's
the purpose, what's the context in which you're doing בדיקת חמץ? bedikat
chametz? You're preparing to get rid of the חמץ, chametz, so מיכל
קאכיל מיניה? meichal ka-achil minei? Are you going to eat the חמץ
chametz at that time? You know, the rabbis say think about the
context, right? Don't think about your interaction with the object directly but
think about your mindset in that time, the whole motivation for the
activity is trying to get rid of חמץ chametz and therefore your
mindset is going to override the לא בדיל lo badeil concern of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the mindset will prevent you from coming
to eat it.
That was how I wanted to answer רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda before
by saying that's how you can answer his position in מנחות Menachot
because in his position in מנחות Menachot he's trying to sell it,
right? It's literally into his property, eating it, that's whether it's supposed
בדיל badiel or לא בדיל lo badeil the context there is different,
in your house you're used to having חמץ chametz you're used to
eating it but like you know in your store you're used to
like perhaps you know trying to like have someone else buy it.
There's a lot of steps along the way though there's the harvesting,
storage, selling it in the store... right right right right.
I would just say sort of as a programmatic comment to that
in just my own thinking about the structure of the סוגיא, sugia,
I think it's often the project of the you know editor of
the ש"ס Shas or the editorial layer of the ש"ס Shas to
try to you know construct
appropriately coherent ways of arraying the positions of the different חכמים chachamim
but what emerges along the way are lots of concepts, you know
many of which might be applied to one or the other and
we could see the other side of it and so you know
all these different things are emerging. The class of an item and
whether that you know makes you less likely to
violate it and therefore גזירה gezeira is not needed or the context
of the activity all these things I think are relevant or the
שינוי shinuy doing something in a different way that heightens your awareness,
you know all these are emerging and they could be applied arguably
in a different way than the גמרא Gemara does apply them, but
this is the layout as it's presented to us. Okay, I see
typically I'm not making a good management of our time, I'll try
to keep going at a good pace.
Okay. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא
קשיא, de-Rabbi Yehuda ad Rabbi Yehuda lo kashya, קמח וקלי תנן. kemach
u-kali tenan.
So רב אשי Rav Ashi now doesn't bring an so right now
we're sort of rolling with אביי'ס Abaye's approach, that the overall you
know in focusing on רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's approach, when do we
need a גזירה? gezeira? Overall we don't need a גזירה gezeira when
someone is already separating from an item. something. And רב אשי's Rav
Ashi now going to try to make a different resolution of this
whole issue which really only emerged because of the contradiction between the
משנה Mishnah in מנחות Menachot about finding the grain out in the
marketplace and our משנה Mishnah in פסחים, Pesachim, right? Out of which
we started to build a general, you know, analysis of רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda position about גזירות, gezeirot, but it's really just a contradiction
between these two משניות. mishnayot. So רב אשי's Rav Ashi going to
try to make a simple resolution. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
רבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא, Rabbi Yehuda ad Rabbi Yehuda lo
kashya, this contradiction between the positions of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda not
a problem. קמח וקלי תנן. Kemach v'kali tnan. What was what was
taught about what's in the marketplace is קמח kemach and קלי. kali.
Let's see, I believe רש"י Rashi comments here. Yep, the second of
the widest lines of רש"י, Rashi, just a few words in. About
ten words in, the second דיבור המתחיל dibur hamatchil on that line:
קמח וקלי תנן ואין אלו ראויין לאכילה. Kemach v'kali tnan v'ein elu
reuyin l'achilah. Right? What's actually out in the marketplace? Flour and these
popped grains or roasted grains. And those things are actually themselves, suggests
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, they're raw materials. They're not in final edible
form, and therefore there is no problem altogether. The reason that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda did not need to make a גזירה gezeirah is
because in every step of the preparation, arguably it seems רב אשי
Rav Ashi is saying, the food, the grain was never in an
edible form, whether it was when it was being harvested, whether it
was when it was being, you know, sifted to make the flour,
or roasted to make the grains. All along the way, it was
never edible and therefore no גזירה gezeirah was needed because there's no
concern דילמא אתי למיכל מיניה dilma atei l'meichal minei that you're going
to come to eat from it. Says the גמרא: Gemara: הא דרב
אשי בדותא היא.
Ha d'Rav Ashi beduta hi. How do they sell it if nobody
eats it? No, but let's but they're only selling it after the
עומר Omer was brought, they're not selling it earlier.
Yes, everyone agrees when you, you know, the right, the shops may
have been being set up, but someone was there saying, no, no,
the עומר Omer hasn't been offered, we're still closed for business. And
when the עומר Omer was offered, then they were open for business.
And so רב אשי Rav Ashi sort of says, let's offer a
technical solution here, which is that the food items were not items
that one needed to make a decree upon because they're not edible
items. הא דרב אשי בדותא היא. Ha d'Rav Ashi beduta hi.
Wait, wait, wait, it says לחם וקלי וכרמל לא תאכלו. lechem v'kali
v'karmel lo tochlu. Okay, good.
Yes, קלי kali certainly sounds like it is an edible item. And
yet רב אשי Rav Ashi seems to believe that it isn't. So
הא דרב אשי בדותא היא. Ha d'Rav Ashi beduta hi. So the
גמרא Gemara says רב אשי's Rav Ashi position is בדותא. beduta. So
we have בדותא beduta in some versions or alternative types of rejections
like this use the language of ברותא, baruta, and they seem to
have two different meanings. בדותא beduta literally means falsified and seems to
be a way of saying, and throughout the generations until today, when
someone finds a position utterly untenable, they'll often try to make the
suggestion בדותא, beduta, the person, the person whose legal authority I trust
must not have really said this. It must have been a student
who misunderstood who said this. So בדותא beduta sort of means this
is made up, this is falsified. But without a way of direct
directly
impugning רב אשי, Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi can't have meant
this. This must have been a falsified made-up decision of רב אשי
Rav Ashi by a student or a misunderstanding or something. Others in
other instances will say ברותא baruta like the language of ברייתא braita
which means outside, which is something along the lines of actually attacking
the position stated by the person who stated it. This belongs outside
the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. This is just completely an unreasonable position.
What's that? Off the wall. Off the wall or beyond the wall,
so to speak. So הא דרב אשי בדותא היא. Ha d'Rav Ashi
beduta hi. And he and we're going to get the argument here.
הא תינח מקלי ואילך מעיקרא ועד קלי מאי איכא. Ha teinach mi'kali
va'eilach mei'ikara v'ad kali mai ika. So it doesn't even take Michael's
position which is that קלי kali is edible. Here they seem to
even agree that קלי kali itself might still not be edible. So
fine, from when it's in the קלי kali form and on, it's
not, you know, there's not a problem. But from the beginning until
קלי, kali, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? At some point in
the preparation of the roasted grain there was some process of softening
it or preparing it at which point there was some point along
the way when it was edible, and at that point there should
have been a decree. And therefore רב אשי's Rav Ashi position is
untenable. There are ראשונים Rishonim or אחרונים Acharonim who raise Michael's question
about no, in fact קלי kali is something which is edible and
some suggest a version of the גמרא Gemara as that the משנה
Mishnah should actually say קמח קלי, kemach kali, not קמח וקלי. kemach
v'kali. But what did they find out in the marketplace? Some kind
of the flour of roasted grain and that indeed there was a
point at which it was קלי kali which was edible, but that
was so quick, they roasted it and then they quickly ground it
into flour and there was really no reasonable moment in which it
could have been edible. And that's that's what רב אשי Rav Ashi
was saying. And then the argument against רב אשי Rav Ashi was
no, even at that point along the way when it was roasted
before it was ground into flour, it might have been able to
be edible. וכי תימא על ידי קיטוף כדרבא אלא קוצרין בין השלחים
ושבעמקים ואוקימנא כרבי יהודה מאי איכא למימר. V'chi teima al yedei kituf
k'd'Rava ela kotrin bein hashlachim v'sheb'amakim v'okimna k'Rabbi Yehuda mai ika l'meimar.
So and if you want to say to this question of, okay,
just answer there was קמח kemach and קלי kali who were which
were not edible, and then we say about that but what about
points beforehand when it was edible, maybe we can give the answer
that we gave before which was that על ידי קיטוף כדרבא, al
yedei kituf k'd'Rava, that there were, you know, all these שינויים shinuyim
in the process up until now. But even so, we still have
to deal with the next משנה Mishnah which we raised, which was
the point in which there was no שינוי shinuy in the process
of harvesting in the other non-עומר Omer
possible fields. And there we established as רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
if you're just going to give a
technical... אלא דרב אשי בדיותא היא. Ela d'Rav Ashi b'dusa hi. So
we really reject רב אשי's Rav Ashi position out of hand. So
we've had רבה's Rabba idea that's sort of based on שינוי, shinuy,
רב אשי's Rav Ashi sort of technical resolution between the two גמרות
Gemaros between the two משניות mishnayot and each of those have been
rejected and we move towards now this really broader, you know
discussion about בדיל מיני bidil minei and לא בדיל מיני lo bidil
minei as the sort of principle upon which we determine whether we
need whether we make a גזירה gezeirah or not. Okay and now
we're going to question that. וכי היכא דלא בדיל מיני מגזר רבי
יהודה? V'chi heicha d'lo bidil minei migzar Rabbi Yehuda? Is it really
true that anywhere where we don't separate from an item רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda does make a decree? So remember רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
position was we make a decree in situations where we're not in
a normal, you know,
separating or guarded attitude towards an item and when we are in
a guarded attitude towards an item there's no גזירה gezeirah necessary. We're
going to also question the second side of that that is it
really true that every time we are in a guarded attitude no
גזירה gezeirah is necessary? But first we're going to tackle the first
one which is that when we're not in a guarded attitude towards
something like חמץ chametz there is a גזירה, gezeirah, right? That's based
on the reading of the משנה mishnah that with חמץ chametz with
which לא בדיל מיני lo bidil minei we don't naturally separate from
it there was a גזירה gezeirah necessary. Now we want to know
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda consistent in that making a גזירה gezeirah
every time we're in a typical relationship with something in order to
avoid interacting it with it in an איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraissa way.
ותנן לא יקוב אדם שפופרת של ביצה וימלאנה שמן ויתננה בצד הנר
בשביל שתהא מנטפת ואפילו היא של חרס ורבי יהודה מתיר.
V'tnan lo yikov adam shfoferet shel beitzah v'yimla'enah shemen v'yitnenah b'tzad haner
bishvil shetehei m'tatefet v'afilu hi shel cheres v'Rabbi Yehuda matir. We'll recognize
this less so in the בית bayit where we don't say במה
מדליקין Bameh Madlikin on שבת Shabbat evenings but from the from the
second פרק perek of משניות mishnayos of שבת Shabbat בפרק במה מדליקין
b'perek Bameh Madlikin in which we say a person should not puncture
a hole in a שפופרת של ביצה shfoferet shel beitzah in an
eggshell וימלאנה שמן v'yimla'enah shemen fill it with oil ויתננה בצד הנר
v'yitnenah b'tzad haner put it alongside the נר. ner. רש"י Rashi reminds
us here very beautifully just for our own clarification נר ner doesn't
mean you know like a wax candle or anything else like that
it means the, you know, something which held oil and had a
wick floating in it that provided light.
And בצד b'tzad next to means next to in some way that
was above or aligned so that בשביל שתהא מנטפת bishvil shetehei m'tatefet
that the oil from the eggshell would fall would, you know, drip
drip drip through that tiny puncture and be able to, you know,
nourish the and and provide additional oil to the lamp lest the
lamp run out. ואפילו היא של חרס V'afilu hi shel cheres even
if that if that eggshell was made out of was made out
of
earthenware ורבי יהודה מתיר v'Rabbi Yehuda matir רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda allows.
So what's going on here? The basic background to this משנה mishnah
is it is actually it is permitted in principle or
or this is really what we're discussing, you know, in theory it's
permitted to set up a little Rube Goldberg device which allows you
to flow extra oil into, you know, let's say you you have
only one candle
candelabrum and it doesn't have enough oil for what you need so
you want to set up some kind of, you know, feeder system.
In principle that would be allowed but the concern is that you're
going to actually, you know, want some of that oil and use
it for your שבת Shabbat meal to, you know, enhance the salad
dressing or something like that and by removing oil out of the
feeder you're actually engaged in an act of מכבה mechabeh of extinguishing
because you're causing there to be less oil available and therefore you're
hastening the extinguishing of the lamp and that's an issue. And the
suggestion is why do we say אפילו היא של חרס? afilu hi
shel cheres? Because as רש"י Rashi comments, you know, if something is
made of earthenware maybe that's, you know, a little bit grosser it's
a little more מאוס ma'us to you and you're not going to
pull oil, right, you're not going to pull the oil out of
an earthenware. An eggshell okay, you know, we people who knows people
might have been eating out of eggshells in general, right, exactly, eggs
out of eggshells but earthenware is already, you know, not something that
you're going to eat out of in this situation and therefore you
might have thought that that would be okay but even out of
earthenware that's how how great the concern is for this potential דאורייתא
d'oraissa whereas it's
a separate discussion to prove that you eat eggs out of eggshells
yes just for clarification
exactly רבי יהודה מתיר Rabbi Yehuda matir whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
seems to allow it, right,
exactly exactly.
I was just going to comment one further thing which is, you
know, and why is why is this such a concern that a
person's actually going to take oil out of there to to the
table quote-unquote and this is here we have to remember
what שבת Shabbat lights are for.
Okay that's what שבת Shabbat lights are for and therefore they were
usually found on the table, right, in our, you know, it's common
in our communities to light שבת Shabbat candles on some separate table,
but, you know, the שבת Shabbat light was to light the meal
so that people had, you know, the capacity to see and and
provide their own and and therefore it's sitting there right there next
to the salad and you're very likely to draw a little oil
off and provide it, you know, and we have that discussion a
lot with oil oil that's used in one thing and a question
can it be used for other things this was a fluid fluid
substance there you go viscous but a fluid. substance whose uses could
be transferred from one thing to another. We generally think about what
you use for light you're not going to use for food; however,
across הלכה Halacha we have those questions in general. So just important
awareness of the setting. Okay, so here it seems like this is
oil is something that we would generally say לא בדיל מיניה. lo
badil minei. You don't look at oil and think it's prohibited for
some reason; it's very accessible, just like חמץ, chametz, a typical foodstuff
or item that you would use normally. And yet so it seems
like Rabbi Yehuda, who is מתיר matir here, does not make a
גזירה gezeira lest you come to
eat the oil, even though we would think he would because oil
is a לא בדיל מיניה lo badil minei substance.
See, what I would have said the answer is that the whole
context is different. You're trying to make this apparatus, right, to put
oil in your candles, as opposed to, you know, I'm seeing חמץ
chametz and I'm used to eating it. I'm not used to eating
oil from an apparatus that's attached to my candle. I'm used to
eating oil from my salad thing, you know, I have a special
thing for that.
Okay, so you could give that answer.
I saw that they actually have one of these things on the
wall. It would look really nice and then they ended up using
it for their salad. I don't know, but that's the whole point,
the point is that it's attached to the
candle and therefore you're not going to use it for your salad,
that's the whole point. But, you know, with oil being such a
transferable substance, there does seem to be this concern. But Rabbi Yehuda
gives a different answer, or the גמרא Gemara gives a different answer
in explaining Rabbi Yehuda: התם משום חומרא דשבת מבדל בדילי. hatam mishum
humra deShabbat mivdal badilei.
So now we have a fascinating principle. Up until now we've been
thinking about בדילי badilei as בדילי badilei from, you know, items as
classified items. But now we have this fascinating concept, because of the
חומרא humra of שבת, Shabbat, the stricture of שבת, Shabbat, מבדל בדילי,
mivdal badilei, we're just we're on we're like a little bit on
edge on שבת. Shabbat. As opposed to פסח?
Pesach?
I don't know.
This is the גמרא's Gemara comment. It's a fair question, it's a
fair question.
Maybe, I don't know, they didn't go nearly as crazy.
Right, maybe that sheds a little light on that idea. But so
because of חומרא דשבת, humra deShabbat, the stricture of שבת, Shabbat, people
are just generally sort of cautious about what they're interacting with and
therefore even though oil is something which people are at ease with,
on שבת Shabbat they would really be cautious. Just an interesting note,
if you have רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel on your דף, daf, about
three quarters of the way down, it's hard to describe exactly where
it is, but about three quarters of the way down on the
right margin where it says the word ביצה, Beitza, it's right across
from about six or eight lines down of רש"י, Rashi, we say
ושנינהו שני שבת דחמיר ליה. vishanina shanei Shabbat dechamir lei. שבת Shabbat
is different because it's strict to him, to the person, which I
think leads to an interesting sort of debate: what is חומרא דשבת?
humra deShabbat? Is חומרא דשבת humra deShabbat that we think the prohibitions
or the punishments or the status of שבת Shabbat is very strict
because it carries such a strict punishment, etc? Then we could really
say חומרא דפסח humra dePesach
is maybe as strict. So חומרא
דשבת humra deShabbat as רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel seems to indicate
is חמיר ליה,
chamir lei, it's strict to the person, we have this relationship
to שבת Shabbat that we're particularly cautious, it's weighty, we take it
seriously, it's just this thing that people are extra careful about and
therefore we're going to separate.
Also as you say, both שבת Shabbat and פסח Pesach have severe
punishments, right? סקילה Sekila and כרת karet are both severe. But maybe
the חומרא humra we're talking about is the structures we've built, the
Rabbis built around שבת, Shabbat, there are many חומרות, humrot, we have
many גזירות gezeirot and so on, so you're always on
edge of
something
you could do wrong,
it's easy to be בונה. bonei. Right, right, גמרא Gemara never heard
of קטניות. kitniyot. Right, right, no I think there is sort of
that sense, which kinds of areas of הלכה Halacha generate not just
an anxiety, I know all the הלכות Halachot but I'm afraid that
I'm going to transgress one of them, as opposed to sort of
an anxiety of I don't even feel that I really know what
I'm doing, I don't trust myself in this area because there could
be all kinds of things that I haven't even heard of that
are prohibited in this area. And sometimes I think שבת Shabbat does
generate that sort of feeling, every time I'm somewhere I learn a
new איסור issur of שבת Shabbat that I didn't even know about.
We often say that in the various areas of הלכה Halacha that
we study in rabbinical school, you know, when it comes to the
area of כשרות, kashrut, oftentimes the more you learn the more you
realize things are not prohibited in the way that you thought. And
the more you learn שבת, Shabbat, the more you realize more things
are prohibited than you realized. There's sort of this sense of חומרא
דשבת humra deShabbat that there are, you know...
What about פסח? Pesach? Good question. I think פסח Pesach the more
you learn
the more you realize that at least people's preparations for פסח Pesach
are stricter than they need to be. Okay, there's a beautiful רב
אבינר Rav Aviner has a beautiful sort of little pamphlet and sheet
about how to clean for שבת, Shabbat, how to clean for פסח
Pesach in a day and a half responsibly and then enjoy yourself.
So there is that pushback as opposed to that YouTube video going
around with foil wrapped around the entire house. So התם משום חומרא
דשבת מבדל בדילי. hatam mishum humra deShabbat mivdal badilei. ורמי שבת דשבת
אשבת. Verami Shabbat deShabbat aShabbat. Now we're going to sort of a
little bit of a tangential aside. Now we're going to sort of
a little bit of a tangential aside to try to resolve a
question about גזירות gezerot within the conversation about שבת shabbat itself. דתניא
חבל דלישא שנפסק לא יהא קושרו אלא עונבו d'tanya chevel d'lisha shenifsak
lo yehei koshro ella onvo רבי יהודה אומר כורך עליו פונדא ופסקיא
ובלבד שלא יענבנו. Rabbi Yehuda omer korech alav punda u'piskiya u'bilvad shelo
ya'anvenu.
So we have a ברייתא braita which says if you have the
rope of a bucket which has broken, come up apart on and
it's שבת, shabbat, לא יהא קושרו, lo yehei koshro, you can't tie
the rope back together, אלא עונבו, ella onvo, rather you can make
some kind of loop, not a knot but some kind of loop.
רבי יהודה אומר כורך עליו פונדא ופסקיא ובלבד שלא יענבנו. Rabbi Yehuda
omer korech alav punda u'piskiya u'bilvad shelo ya'anvenu. Rabbi Yehuda seems stricter.
He says you can take some a sash or a belt or
something like that and you can sort of wrap it and maybe
even maybe even tie it with a temporary kind of tie. Remember
on שבת shabbat what's prohibited is קשר של קיימא, kesher shel kayama,
an enduring, which we at least translate as something which will last
till after שבת, shabbat, an enduring kind of knot, but temporary is
not prohibited. So we have this Rabbi Yehuda's position is you can't
even make a loop, you can't even reconnect with using only the
two sides of the rope, but you can take some third item
and tie it even with some kind of temporary knot or or
a loop, something which would be prohibited for the two sides of
the rope itself but with a third item wrapping around you can.
קשיא דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה קשיא דרבנן אדרבנן. Kashya d'Rabbi Yehuda a'd'Rabbi
Yehuda kashya d'Rabbanan a'd'Rabbanan. So now we have a question of Rabbi
Yehuda on Rabbi Yehuda and רבנן אדרבנן. Rabbanan a'd'Rabbanan. Rabbi Yehuda who
does here seem to
be more strict whereas he allowed in the case
of the eggshell feeding into the lamp and here he does seem
to be more concerned lest you come to make a real קשר
של קיימא kesher shel kayama
you can't even loop, whereas חכמים Chachamim who were stricter there seem
to be lenient here and not concerned that in making the עניבה,
aniva, the loop, you would come to make a real קשירה. keshira.
Here the assumption is that every case of שבת shabbat will be
the same as every other case of שבת shabbat in terms of
lining up the שיטות shitot of the חכמים. Chachamim.
Yes, yes, exactly. Yes, thank you for saying that. ורמי שבת דשבת
אשבת Verami shabbat d'shabbat a shabbat does is based on that presumption
that שבת shabbat is one.
Yes, or you're supposed to differentiate the situation.
Yes, thank you very much good. And so the answer is לא
קשיא שמן בשמן מחלף עניבה בקשירה לא מחלף. lo kashya shemen b'shemen
michlaf aniva b'keshira lo michlaf. Sorry, so דרבנן אדרבנן לא קשיא שמן
בשמן מחלף עניבה בקשירה לא מחלף. d'Rabbanan a'd'Rabbanan lo kashya shemen b'shemen
michlaf aniva b'keshira lo michlaf. So the position of the Rabbis, and
it's an interesting interesting here seems to uphold Rav Dov's point. The
resolution that we present is not really a resolution about differentiating between
contexts of שבת shabbat but between contexts of objects that we might
interact with. And we're saying that שמן בשמן מחלף, shemen b'shemen michlaf,
the reason that the Rabbis are stricter when it comes to the
oil situation of not allowing you to to set up the feeder
oil lest you come to take out for your food, is because
oils, they're oil is oil and you're going to come to interchange
between the oil of the lamp and the oil that you might
use at your table.
עניבה בקשירה לא מחלף, Aniva b'keshira lo michlaf, but making a loop
is not even remotely the same activity as making a knot and
therefore we're not concerned that in making a loop you're going to
come to make a knot. דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא טעמא
דרבי יהודה לאו משום דגזר עניבה אטו קשירה אלא משום דקסבר עניבה
גופא קשירה היא. D'Rabbi Yehuda a'd'Rabbi Yehuda lo kashya ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda
lav mishum d'gazar aniva atu keshira ella mishum d'kasavar aniva gufa keshira
hi. And Rabbi Yehuda's again a sort of a technical resolution. There's
not really a conceptual difference between the two for Rabbi Yehuda. Rabbi
Yehuda in general is sort of is permissive and and the reason
that he's strict in the case of the tying is not because
he's it's not that he's concerned that looping will lead to tying,
but he actually thinks of עניבה, aniva, of looping, as essentially tying.
He thinks of עניבה aniva of that what we think of as
a milder tie as really a a formal tie and therefore he's
strict there. They actually think of what the status of עניבה aniva
is differently. ורמי רבנן אדרבנן, Verami Rabbanan a'd'Rabbanan,
now we're sort of descending into a deeper sub-analysis within שבת shabbat
to try to sort out the רבנן Rabbanan's position. We're a little
bit away now from the sorting out of Rabbi Yehuda's overall conceptual
framework of when we make גזירות, gezerot, but we make this now
a tack between the positions of
רבנן. Rabbanan. ורמי רבנן אדרבנן דשבת, Verami Rabbanan a'd'Rabbanan d'shabbat, because we're
still in the realm of שבת. shabbat. דתנן קושרין דלי בפיסקייא אבל
לא בחבל רבי יהודה מתיר. d'tnan koshrin deli b'piskiya aval lo b'chevel
Rabbi Yehuda matir.
So we have the position רבנן Rabbanan say that you can tie
the bucket with a with this פיסקייא piskiya but not with a
rope, and Rabbi Yehuda permits. First we need to clarify the circumstance.
חבל דמאי? Chevel d'mai? If we would say it's regular old rope
and Rabbi Yehuda is allowing it here,
רבי יהודה מתיר קשר של קיימא הוא דודאי אתי לבטולי, Rabbi Yehuda
matir kesher shel kayama hu d'vadai atei l'batulei, what kind of rope
is it? If we say it's a general rope and yet we
have the position that Rabbi Yehuda is allowing it, אלא פשיטא דגרדי.
ella peshita d'gardi. But this would be a קשר של קיימא kesher
shel kayama because you're certainly going to leave a general rope in
place there. אלא פשיטא דגרדי. Ela p'shita d'gardi. This must be a
kind of rope that you're not going to leave there. And so
we don't have the concern that it's a קשר של קיימא kesher
shel kayama
because contextually, circumstantially, you're going to take the rope away. And therefore,
it must be דגרדי, d'gardi, a weaver's rope, which is some kind
of rope, which again has a professional use, it's not just lying
around for utility, but has a professional use of weavers, and therefore
it might be used temporarily, but it's going to be removed immediately.
וגזרו רבנן חבל דגרדי אטו חבל דעלמא? V'gazru Rabbanan chevel d'gardi atu
chevel d'alma?
And רבנן Rabbanan make this decree of the weaver's rope for rope
in general?
אין. In. חבל בחבל מחלף, אניבה בקשירה לא מחלפא. Chevel b'chevel michlaf,
aniva b'kshira lo michlafa. So we resolve by saying, again, types of
ropes, in terms of resolving the position of the רבנן, Rabbanan, various
kinds of ropes could be interchanged with one another, but אניבה בקשירה
לא מחלפא, aniva b'kshira lo michlafa, a looping and tying are not
things which would lead one to another and that separates out the
positions of רבנן. Rabbanan. Let's just go a little further. וכל היכא
דבדילי מיניה לא גזר רבי יהודה? V'chol heicha d'badilei minei lo gazar
Rabbi Yehuda? Okay, so we've now seemed to have resolved the question.
We had a counterexample, just remember a little further up we said,
וכל היכא דלא בדילי מיניה מי גזר רבי יהודה? V'chol heicha d'lo
badilei minei mi gazar Rabbi Yehuda? Does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda really
make a decree every place we are not on guard with things,
every place we interact normally with things? And we raised the question
of שמן, shemen, and we resolved that because of חומרא דשבת, chumra
d'Shabbat, בדילי מיניה, badilei minei, and therefore that was not a counterexample.
Now we're going to query the other side. וכל היכא דבדילי מיניה,
V'chol heicha d'badilei minei, is it really true that every place where
we do separate from something, where we are on guard about something,
לא גזר רבי יהודה? lo gazar Rabbi Yehuda? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
doesn't feel the need to decree because the בדילי מיניה badilei minei
resolves the issue? והתניא, V'hatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא, braita,
בכור שאחזו דם אפילו הוא מת אין מקיזין לו דם דברי רבי
יהודה, וחכמים אומרים יקיז ובלבד שלא יטיל בו מום? Bechor she'achazo dam
afilu hu met ein makizin lo dam divrei Rabbi Yehuda, va'chachamim omrim
yakiz u'vilvad shelo yatil bo mum? So we have a ברייתא braita
about a בכור, bechor, so we're talking about a firstborn animal which
belongs to the, which belongs to the כהן, kohen, שאחזו דם, she'achazo
dam, which was taken hold of by an excess of blood. Remember,
this was a condition of medical concern in rabbinic times of having
what seemed to be too much blood and that required bloodletting. And
we say, אפילו הוא מת, afilu hu met, even if the animal
is going to die, אין מקיזין לו דם, ein makizin lo dam,
we can't do the bloodletting, says רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Even though
bloodletting in particular areas of the body, so remember bloodletting required some
kind of prick or some kind of wounding the animal, so to
speak, in order to allow the blood to come out. Now, if
you did bloodletting by cutting off the animal's leg, then you've created
a מום mum in a בכור, bechor, which is not allowed. You're
not allowed to put a מום mum upon a בכור. bechor. And
therefore, doing the bloodletting there would be a problem. But if you
just made a little prick in the animal's side and allowed the
blood to flow out, because that's not going to be a permanent
harm to the animal, that will just grow back exactly as it
looked before, therefore there's not a problem of causing a מום mum
to an animal. So in principle, one should be able to do
the bloodletting in a place where a מום mum is not going
to be created. And yet רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda seems not to
allow it. And this is going to be our question. בכור Bechor
obviously we would think of as בדילי מיניה. badilei minei. A בכור
bechor is something which we have a lot of hesitation and we're
on guard about not to cause it a מום, mum, it's not
something which can be used by a non-כהן, kohen, etc. So it's
in the בדילי מיניה badilei minei category, and yet רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda seems to be גוזר. gozer. And therefore that's our question. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is גוזר, gozer, sets an extra decree upon something
which we normally would separate from. וחכמים V'chachamim say, no, יקיז, yakiz,
you can allow, you can do the bloodletting, ובלבד שלא יטיל בו
מום, u'vilvad shelo yatil bo mum, just be cautious not to do
it in such a way that would cause a מום. mum. So
this seems to oppose the position that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't
need to make a גזירה gezera in a case of
בדילי מיניה. badilei minei. התם משום שאדם בהול, Hatam mishum she'adam bahul,
onto the second side, sorry, got to go a lot of pages
on the ArtScroll, על ממונו, al mamono, אמרינן אי שרית ליה במקום
שאין עושין
בו מום אתי למעבד במקום שעושין בו מום.
amrinan ei sharit lei b'makom she'ein
osin bo mum ati l'mevad b'makom she'osin bo mum.
So why is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda make גזירה gezera in a
case of בדילי מיניה? badilei minei? This case, this בדילי מיניה badilei
minei case of בכור, bechor, the animal of the כהן, kohen, is
already a different category. Why? Because אדם בהול על ממונו. adam bahul
al mamono. We have this general principle, I don't remember if it
may have even come up already in פסחים, Psachim, that a person
is very worried about their assets, about their money. And therefore, here
we're talking about the כהן. kohen. The כהן kohen is very
concerned, hasn't even been given to the כהן kohen yet, right, could
be that. And then you see... he has this excess of blood,
I don't let it blood-let it, because I know it's going to
the כהן Kohen anyway and I'm probably going to lose that. Interesting.
Is it only the כהן Kohen who's worried about his money?
Right. Yes. It does seem to be the כהן. Kohen. Yes. Yes.
So the כהן Kohen who's בהול על ממונו, bahul al mamono, although
I don't it's interesting, I'm not sure what the in general with
a בכור, Bechor, what what you're allowed to how much jurisdiction you
have over it before you give it to the כהן. Kohen. I
don't know what, you know, I don't know about that that's an
interesting question. But so the כהן Kohen here is concerned about the
about the animal. Remember, and the first רש"י Rashi on עמוד ב׳
Amud Bet explains this: כהן זה בהול על בכור שלא ימות. Kohen
zeh bahul al Bechor shelo yamut. Right? Once the once the even
if it gets a מום, mum, one could שחט shecht it and
use it, but once the בכור Bechor does die, it's of no
monetary value to the כהן Kohen anymore. And so the כהן Kohen
is what's that?
Can he use a whip? Or is that possible?
I'm not sure. Good question. I'm not sure about the more parameters
of the בכור Bechor here.
So because the כהן Kohen is concerned that the animal not die,
we say אי שרי ליה במקום שאינו עושה בו מום אתי למיעבד
במקום שעושה בו מום. i sharei lei bemakom she-eino oseh bo mum,
ati le-me'evad bemakom she-oseh bo mum. And the and the idea of
בהול על ממונו bahul al mamono it's not just concern, but בהול
bahul sort of like worked up and sort of anxious about his
money. And therefore the כהן's Kohen so nervous about it, that for
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we have to make the גזירה gezeirah because
if we allowed the כהן Kohen to do it in a place
where one wouldn't make a מום, mum, which would be, you know,
no problem at all in principle, let's say it didn't work, the
כהן's Kohen getting anxious and nervous and is just going to start,
you know, bloodletting anywhere, and he's not going to be able to
make this clear distinction. So there's sort of a mindset issue. Indeed,
we are בדיל badil from from קדשים Kadshim and from the בכור,
Bechor, however there's this a principle that overrides the בדיל badil principle,
which is the בהול bahul principle. When one's worried about one's money,
one can't, you know, be one can't be trusted to sort of
set up a line that that would obviate the need for a
גזירה, gezeirah, so we replace that but we we we address that
בהול bahul concern or worry of ours, legal worry, with the גזירה,
gezeirah, says רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. ורבנן, Verabbanan, כל שכן דאי לא
שרי ליה כלל אתי למיעבד. kolsheken de-i lo sharei lei klal, ati
le-me'evad. רבנן Rabbanan have a sort of fascinating counter-argument, which I think
we often think about legally. If you don't allow him to do
anything, then he's going to it's even worse, right? This כהן Kohen
is staring at his animal and he's so, so anxious, you know,
so let him do something and, you know, and then you can
at least trust him, you've relieved some of that anxiety by giving
him a permissible option, he's not going you know, and that's a
better way of avoiding him doing a prohibited option. So it's an
interesting sort of debate when you're really concerned that someone doesn't have
boundaries, they're so anxious, בהול על ממונו, bahul al mamono, they don't
have boundaries, should you give them the permissible option because that'll at
least relieve the anxiety, or really prohibit everything because you can't trust
them to do anything? So it's an interesting debate.
Sort of like a גזירה שאין הציבור
יכול לעמוד בה. gezeirah she-ein ha-tzibur yakhol la-amod bah.
Right,
we don't right, we don't make a decree that that, you know,
is unmanageable for the רוב הציבור, rov ha-tzibur, or maybe in this
case even for an individual or that community of כהנים. kohanim. Maybe
that's what's motivating חכמים. hachamim.
Let's make it to the משנה. Mishna. I mean, and if that's
at play, if that is at play, then it actually means that
in principle the חכמים hachamim and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, according to
the תלמוד Talmud here, would agree with each other that a גזירה
gezeirah would be desirable.
Right, but what can you do? חכמים: Hachamim: human nature. Yes. Yes.
Let's make it to the משנה.
Mishna. Okay, good.
Yeah, because the the גמרא Gemara on the משנה Mishna is a
pretty quick flow, so if we get to the משנה Mishna we
should be in better shape. So, okay.
Fourth line in the middle. ומי אמרינן לרבי יהודה אדם בהול על
ממונו? Umi amrinan leRabbi Yehuda adam bahul al mamono? Do we really
have this principle? So we explained רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the reason
that he made a גזירה gezeirah is because the concern of אדם
בהול על ממונו adam bahul al mamono overrode the בדיל מיניה. badil
minei. Is this really true? והתנן Vehatnan רבי יהודה אומר אין מקדרין
Rabbi Yehuda omer ein mekadrin or
מקרדין mekardin הבהמה ביום טוב מפני שהוא עושה חבורה, ha-behemah beyom tov
mipnei shehu oseh haburah, אבל מקרצין aval mekartzin וחכמים אומרים אין מקדרין
אף אין מקרצין. vachachamim omrim ein mekadrin af ein mekartzin. So we
have various kinds of combs that we use to pull out fleas
or maybe רש"י Rashi suggests it's to get, you know, dirt or
some kind of plaster, something like that out of the animal. And
we and we do that, but the concern is that, right, מפני
שהוא עושה חבורה, mipnei shehu oseh haburah, the concern is that if
you have a really heavy comb, in the process of combing you're
actually going to bruise the animal and that's that's prohibited on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So what's the motivation for doing this? The motivation
is that actually when it's when there's all that stuff in, you
know, that's that's in the animal, there's a there's the animal's discomfort,
but there may also be a health risk and that's that's another
factor that motivates us to want to do it even on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, we don't want to wait, but we we don't
want to do it in a way that's going to cause a
חבורה. haburah. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says here that one can
go part way, one can do the the way that's not going
to cause the חבורה, haburah, which is the מקרדין mekardin or מקדרין.
mekadrin.
Sorry, he says we don't we don't do the one that's going
to cause the חבורה, haburah, and that seems to be with a
metal one, but we can do it with these wooden larger-toothed comb,
we can. וחכמים אומרים אין מקדרין אף אין מקרצין. vachachamim omrim ein
mekadrin af ein mekartzin. He says we don't we don't do the
one that's going to cause the חבורה chaburah but we can do
and that seems to be with a metal one but we can
do with this wooden larger-toothed comb we can. וחכמים אומרים אין מקרדין
ואף אין מקרצפין. VeChachamim omrim ein mekadrin ve'af ein mekartsfin. We can't
do anything. דתניא Detanya we taught in a ברייתא Baraisa איזו היא
קידור ואיזו היא קרצוף? eizu hi kidor ve'eizu hi kirtsuf? What is
each of these combing methods? קידור קטנים ועושים חבורה. kidor ketanim ve'osim
chaburah. A קידור kidor is the is the combing with the very
fine toothed tiny little teeth and it is liable to make a
wound and I think some suggest even it's a difference of metal
and wood and קרצוף גדולים ואין עושים חבורה. kartsuf gedolim ve'ein osim
chaburah. So it's a not a fine toothed comb but a whatever
the opposite is a loosely toothed and large-toothed comb and is not
going to make a חבורה. chaburah. And therefore we see but here
too we would think that a person is בהול על ממונו. bahul
al mamono. They see their animal is you know got all this
stuff caught up in its skin and it could you know harm
the animal and therefore we would think a person would want to
do this and if we're concerned that בהול על ממונו bahul al
mamono we would think that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would make a
decree here not to allow
anything. התם דאי שבקיה מיית אמרינן אדם בהול על ממונו הכא אי
שבקיה צערא בעלמא הוא לא אמרינן אדם בהול על ממונו. Hatam de'ei
shavkia mayit amrinan adam bahul al mamono hacha ei shavkia tsa'ara be'alma
hu lo amrinan adam bahul al mamono. So there's clearly a distinction
between the case of the בכור bechor where with needing to bleed
let we're concerned the animal is going to die therefore a person
is really concerned about ממונו mamono whereas here in the case of
you know in the case of the you know pain of the
animal it's interesting of course we know חכמים Chachamim were very concerned
about the pain of the animal but you know it maybe the
owner wasn't actually as concerned about the pain of the animal and
therefore it doesn't rise to that בהול על ממונו bahul al mamono
type of concern. There is going to be pain to the animal
but it's not really liable to you know at risk of death
etc. רבי יהודה מאי שנא גבי חמץ דגזר ומאי שנא גבי קרצוף
דלא גזר? Rabbi Yehuda mai shna gabei chametz degazar umai shna gabei
kartsuf delo gazar? So now going all the way back to contrast
this one the case of קרצוף kirtsuf where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is not גוזר gozer and the case of חמץ chametz where we
are concerned that the person is going to come to eat the
חמץ chametz and again this is your regular old animal so this
seems to be a case of לא בדיל מיניה. lo badil minei.
You're at ease with the thing and in a case of לא
בדיל מיניה lo badil minei where we're concerned that you're going to
come to violate a דאורייתא de'oraisa then we should make a גזירה.
gezeirah. So what so this seems to be the last attack on
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's overall principle as אביי Abaye framed it as
having to do with בדיל מיניה. badil minei. Why does רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda make that concern make the גזירה gezeirah about חמץ chametz
and not here? לחם בלחם מחלף קידור בקרצוף לא מחלף. Lechem belechem
michlaf kidor bekirtsuf lo michlaf. You know the breads of prohibited and
permitted one easily could exchange. You're looking at bread you're not making
distinctions but קידור kidor and קרצוף kirtsuf these two different methods לא
מחלף lo michlaf we're not concerned that one is going to lead
to the other. So we wind up with this אביי Abaye sort
of taking the day that overall a person we have the idea
that when you are liable to an איסור דאורייתא isur de'oraisa we
do want to make a גזירה gezeirah if it's something that you're
not already on guard about. However it does depend on whether the
item that you're interacting with you know is something which is easily
going to lead from the permitted to the prohibited or not and
we have this broad framework of the way רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is thinking about גזירות gezeiros as well as חכמים Chachamim even though
we focus on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we also have the other
side which is all of חכמים's Chachamim's approaches in enacting גזירה. gezeira.
Okay we'll pause here.
יישר כוח Yasher koach everyone. Thank you. Thank you. I don't think
that's a strong סברא. sevara. I would say the opposite. לחם בלחם
לא מחלף. Lechem belechem lo michlaf. You come to eat חמץ chametz
you're eating מצה. matzah. Right. Right. Right. You're eating מצה matzah you're
going to it's going to be in your
hand you're going to know this is not חמץ.
chametz. Right. Right. Whereas you're going to work with a כלי kli
you're going to say this
כלי kli is not working I'm going to switch with another כלי.
kli.